<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Nebulo Anglicanus, or, The first part of the black life of John Gadbury it is the same John Gadbury that was in the Popish Plot to murther Charles II in the year 1678 : it is the same John Gadbury that was accused of being in another plot, to dethrone and destroy King William, in the year 1690 : it is the same John Gadbury that at this time is so strait-lac'd in conscience that he cannot take the oaths to their majesties : together with an answer to a late pamphlet of his / by J. Partridge.</title>
            <author>Partridge, John, 1644-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56512</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P622</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6007</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12798412</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12798412</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94020</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56512)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94020)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 725:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Nebulo Anglicanus, or, The first part of the black life of John Gadbury it is the same John Gadbury that was in the Popish Plot to murther Charles II in the year 1678 : it is the same John Gadbury that was accused of being in another plot, to dethrone and destroy King William, in the year 1690 : it is the same John Gadbury that at this time is so strait-lac'd in conscience that he cannot take the oaths to their majesties : together with an answer to a late pamphlet of his / by J. Partridge.</title>
                  <author>Partridge, John, 1644-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 28 p. : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and are to be sold by the booksellers of London and Westminster,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"An answer to his idle pamphlet" p. 15.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gadbury, John, 1627-1704. --  Merlini liberati errata.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94020:1"/>
            <p>NEBULO ANGLICANUS<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Or, The Firſt Part of the BLACK LIFE OF <hi>Iohn Gadbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the Same <hi>JOHN GADB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RY</hi> That was in the Popiſh Plot to murther <hi>Charles</hi> II. in the Year 1678.</p>
            <p>It is the Same <hi>JOHN GADBURY</hi> That was accuſed of being in another Plot, to dethrone and deſtroy King <hi>William,</hi> in the Year 1690.</p>
            <p>It is the Same <hi>JOHN GADBURY</hi> That at this Time is ſo ſtrait-lac'd in Conſcience that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not take the Oaths to their Preſent Majeſties.</p>
            <p>Together with an Anſwer to a Late Pamphlet of His.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. PARTRIDGE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I have fought with Beaſts after the manner of Men,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed, and are to be ſold by the Bookſellers of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:94020:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Merlinus Verax.</head>
                  <q>a specic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> protestant.</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <l>Good People pity me, for I'm half mad,</l>
            <l>Both <hi>Fool</hi> and <hi>Knave,</hi> and every thing that's bad:</l>
            <l>Beget by Chance, my <hi>Stars</hi> with Loves ſoft arm</l>
            <l>(No Prieſt concern'd) <hi>gave</hi> Figure to the Sperm.</l>
            <l>My <hi>Furious Form</hi> thus laid, her ſullen Womb,</l>
            <l>Preſerv'd the <hi>wonder</hi> of the Age to come;</l>
            <l>I've liv'd in Vice and Tricking all my days,</l>
            <l>And I'll be any thing to live in Eaſe;</l>
            <l>I'll be a <hi>Heathen, Proteſtant,</hi> or <hi>Jew,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>A <hi>Turk,</hi> a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> any thing that's new;</l>
            <l>Let but the <hi>Prieſts</hi> of my Religion ſay it,</l>
            <l>Go <hi>Swear,</hi> or <hi>Kill,</hi> I'll certainly obey it;</l>
            <l>My Crimes (Pox take my Fate) I can't diſown,</l>
            <l>There's nothing vexeth me, but that they're known;</l>
            <l>Nay, many <hi>Vices</hi> more infect my Will;</l>
            <l>But my Diſcretion keeps them ſeeret ſtill;</l>
            <l>Well, pray for me <hi>(Romes Saints)</hi> 'tis that I crave,</l>
            <l>A poor <hi>fall'n Brother,</hi> but all over <hi>Slave;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And in my good old Shape too, I'll appear,</l>
            <l>Your <hi>Thimble Prophet,</hi> and your <hi>Bodkin Seer.</hi>
            </l>
            <pb facs="tcp:94020:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:94020:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94020:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE Moſt Exquiſitly Accompliſh'd IN <hi>Plotting, Tricking,</hi> AND INGRATITUDE, My Honoured Friend, Mr. <hi>John Thimble,</hi> of <hi>Brick-Court.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe Your Inſolency,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T of a horrible reſpect to Your Ignorance, and want of Merit, as well as Vertue and Honeſty, I have made bold to borrow a Grain from your vaſt Treaſury of Impudence, to qualifie and render me more acceptable to your ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbious Tutorſhip; and that by the help of your Frowns I may more careleſly approach your Imperious Carkaſs, to kiſs your Fiſt of Violence with this ſmall bundle of Gratitude, and with a great deal of Submiſſion (for I know you expect Surreve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence;) I humbly deſire you to remember how grateful you were to Mr. <hi>Lilly,</hi> your <hi>Kind</hi> and <hi>Generous Maſter,</hi> that reſcued you from the <hi>Thimble-Diſpenſation,</hi> and taught you how to get meat to your Bread, that being (you know) the Firſt and Second Courſe, when you lived within leſs than a Mile of <hi>Strand-Bridge;</hi> and after this and abundance more of Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb facs="tcp:94020:4"/>
which you have acknowledged in Print, the worſt Word in your Budget was too good for him; and you have abuſed him who was your <hi>Maſter,</hi> as much as you have done <hi>Me,</hi> that You ſay was your <hi>Pupil. Hah Jack, Gratitude, Gratitude! Maſter</hi> and <hi>Pupil</hi> both ſuffer alike, no Mercy in <hi>Brick Court.</hi> And ſo I take my Leave of my Confoundedly Learned <hi>Pythagor-Aſs,</hi> and both with Goad and Awl I ſhall attend your Thimble and Bodkin, and am ready to ſerve You, while I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:94020:4"/>
            <head>To the Impartial READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friend, or no Friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have lately met with a Scandalous Invidious Pamphlet, ſent into the World without a Name (called <hi>Merlini Liberati Erra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta</hi>) as if the Author of it, either for Scandalous Crimes, or other Villanies, were aſham'd to let the World know from whence it came, and alſo would very fain have the World believe it was done by ſome Friend to <hi>J. G.</hi> one that is willing to defend him, that is either unable, or aſham'd to defend himſelf: But whoſoever hath had any Converſation with Mr. <hi>John Thimble,</hi> will eaſily gueſs who ſpawn'd this ſpurious Brat, for it is as like its <hi>Dad,</hi> as if it had been digg'd out of his A — with a Pick-Axe: In a word, it came from our <hi>Popiſh-Proteſtant Conjurer</hi> in <hi>Brick Court.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore, good Reader, pardon the Entertainment I muſt here give you of ſuch a Fulſome and Nauſeous Subject; and pray pity me that muſt endure the Stench of raking into the Vicious Actions, and worſe Converſation of a <hi>Dung-hill Fellow,</hi> that ſtinks in the Norſtrils of all good and ſober people: A <hi>Fellow</hi> that is a Scandal to Humanity, a <hi>Satyr</hi> upon Vertue, a <hi>Hater</hi> of Truth, a <hi>Promoter</hi> of Slavery, a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> in Maſquerade, a <hi>Renegado</hi> in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; <hi>unkind</hi> to thoſe that have ſerved him, <hi>unjuſt</hi> to his Wife, <hi>unchaſt</hi> in his Converſation, <hi>unfaithful</hi> to his Friend, <hi>treacherous</hi> to his Prince, and a <hi>Sworn Enemy</hi> to the Religion and Liberties of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I know very well that Contention of this nature is never welcome in <hi>Print</hi> to Mankind in general; nor had I took the pains of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, or given you the trouble of reading theſe <hi>Sheets</hi> of <hi>Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,</hi> had it not been to juſtifie my ſelf from the Aſperſions of my Adverſary, who hath beſpattered me with Falſhood; and to tell you the Truth, he is a Common Lyar.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:94020:5"/>If you meet with any Rough <hi>Words,</hi> or <hi>Perſonal</hi> and <hi>Mechanical Reflections</hi> in the Pages following, I deſire you to read the mover with a charitable and friendly Cenſure; for I do aſſure you there is not any thing of that nature but what falls from my Pen unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, and was forcibly drawn from me by his ſoul and ſcurrilous Language; and in reference to Mechanical Reflections, as my Pen never quarrelled till his threw down the Gantlet, ſo I never touch'd upon thoſe till he broke the Ice: So that you ſee he is ſtill the Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor in all things of this Nature.</p>
            <p>As to his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nskilfulneſs</hi> in his <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> his <hi>Self-contradiction, Falſe</hi> and <hi>Ignorant Aſſertions</hi> in <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> and <hi>Confuſed Rules</hi> and <hi>Aphoriſms, ſtolen, aſſerted,</hi> and <hi>applied,</hi> I do not think fit to publiſh them in ſuch a Treatiſe as this is, but in one where they ſhall remain not for a Year, but for an Age, and to be read by ſuch perſons as will be competent Judges in the Matter, whether I ſpeak Truth, or not.</p>
            <p>But I will here take the Liberty to remind him and the World of one thing, ſince he hath endeavoured to make me appear ſo igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and ſilly a Fellow as he doth; and that is in his Epiſtle to my <hi>Vade Mecum;</hi> where he ſays, <q>This Learned Epitomy of Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, here preſented unto thee (Worthy Reader) is a moſt Exact and genuine Piece of Art, free from Impurity and Falſhood; Thou haſt here the Oar of Science without the Droſs; the True Wine without the Dregs; and all the Parts of this Moſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and Uſeful Learning ſo well and judiciouſly methodiſed, and ſo neatly and curiouſly handled by our Author, in a Vein ſo modeſt and taking, without perplexing his Matter with any thing impertinent and uſeleſs, that this Book alone is ſufficient to make thee a Competent Artiſt in every part of Aſtrology — — In a word, there is nothing wanting but our Thanks to the Author for his <hi>Great Care<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and <hi>Pains</hi> taken therein.</q> Now I ſuppoſe no man will doubt but he meant what he ſaid at that time; if ſo, it is a wonder I ſhould be ſo much altered (as he ſeems to infer and prove in his late Libel) and grown leſs skilful. If I did deſerve that Commendation then, he is an ill man to endeavour to pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the contrary now; if I d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d not deſerve it then, he was a Fool or a Kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve to give it.</p>
            <p>But in a ſhort time you will have a full and a fair Account of our <hi>Brick-Court Aſtrologer,</hi> where he ſhall appear the moſt Ignorant man that ever pretended to the Art in Print.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By Your Friend <hi>J.P.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94020:5"/>
            <head>A Short ACCOUNT Of a Few REMARKABLE PASSAGES IN THE EDUCATION and LIFE Of Honeſt <hi>J. G.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WE ſee plainly that Nature hath not bound her ſelf to a particular Method in the Order and Way of Generation in all Creatures, but ſports her ſelf in the Variety and Order both as to Time, and Method, juſt as ſhe doth in the Colours of Herbs and Flowers: A <hi>Fly-blow</hi> on a <hi>Cabbage</hi> turns to a <hi>Maggot,</hi> and afterwards to a <hi>Butterfly</hi> with curious Colours. Serpents lay their Eggs, and they are hatch'd by the heat of the Dung, or ſome other hot Soyl; They tell us of a ſort of Creature in <hi>India,</hi> that when they conceive, the Female bites off the Male's Head; and when the young ones are ripe for Production, they are not brought forth like other Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but gnaw their way through the Damm's Belly. <hi>Cats</hi> are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry modeſt in Coition, and always do it privately; but <hi>Dogs</hi> and their Kind generate openly in the Streets with a ſort of Impudence, as ſome other Creatures do. Hence the <hi>Poet</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vipers</hi> bring <hi>Vipers</hi> forth, by this I find</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bitches</hi> get <hi>Puppies</hi> to ſupply their Kind.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>It is no Scandal for any of the <hi>Divine <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania's</hi> Servants either to be a <hi>By-blow,</hi> or <hi>got,</hi> or <hi>born</hi> at a venture, without the conſent either of Prieſt or Pariſh; nor is every one bound to wait for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency of Chamber-Furniture, or the Invitation of the Kindred;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94020:6"/>
Sometimes a <hi>Tayler</hi> waiting to try the <hi>Lady's Stays,</hi> lets fly at the Game, and receives the Fertile Product of his Labour at Nine Months end. They ſay an ill <hi>Bird</hi> lays an ill <hi>Egg:</hi> If ſo, the <hi>Brood</hi> muſt be of the ſame Nature that is thence produced. You ſee Children born of dull heavy Parents, how ſtupid and blockiſh they naturally are; and that <hi>Baſtards</hi> are generally brisk and airy, and alſo promoters of the ſame way that gave them their Being. I know a <hi>Hero</hi> born of an <hi>Illuſtrious Dam,</hi> who had a peculiar way to conſecrate Noſegays to borrow money with; you'll wonder how, I'll warrant you; and indeed ſo you may very well; — and ſo let's enter <hi>Don Phylo Mathematicus, Secretary</hi> and <hi>Buffoon</hi> to the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania,</hi> who was born <hi>December</hi> 31ſt. between the Old Year and the New, as if Nature had form'd him for a Squint-ey'd Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelite, always looking two ways; or like a Waterman, that looks one way, and rows another; one that was doom'd by his Stars to draw his Religion once a year, as people do Valentines by lot; and alſo defends the Faith he hath drawn, till the Seaſon comes again for him to draw a new one.</p>
            <p>This Little <hi>Furioſo,</hi> while in Swadling Cloaths, gave early De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations of his reſpect to Religion; for where-ever he ſaw a <hi>Croſs</hi> (eſpecially a gilded one) he would always make a <hi>Reverend Bow</hi> to it, which gave his Mother (who was a Papiſt) mighty hopes of his future Perfection in the Old Faith; nor did there want early Arguments of his <hi>Fertile Fancy,</hi> and <hi>Quick Parts,</hi> for they ſay he would often B— two or three Clouts before his Nurſe could waſh one. Likewiſe when he did arrive at the growth of a <hi>Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Stool,</hi> he was immediately hammering at the crabbed Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Silly-giſms, Dilemma</hi>'s, <hi>Arks</hi> and <hi>Semediameters;</hi> ſo that his indulgent Parents began to think of ſending this little Elf to the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> before he was corrupted with the <hi>Education</hi> of his Hornbook.</p>
            <p>And indeed this was ſoon put in practice afterwards, and away they ſent him to <hi>St. Nicholi</hi>'s Colledge, where by the help of a good <hi>Tutor,</hi> and a <hi>whetting Diet,</hi> this little Thief grew as ſharp as a Needle, to the admiration of all the Fellows of that Houſe, and the circumadjacent Colledges, who ſpent their time in that kind of <hi>Study;</hi> ſo that it was generally agreed on as a Gratitude to his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and for the Reputation of his Parts, to confer on him that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Title of <hi>Louſy Jack;</hi> and under this Reputation he was for ſome time made <hi>Runner General</hi> for the whole Society, where he ſpent a few years to make him fit to take his Degrees at <hi>London;</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:94020:6"/>
to which place he came at a good ſuitable Age, as you ſhall ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly hear more at large.</p>
            <p>To compleat his Crimes in the future part of his Life, to <hi>London</hi> comes our <hi>Academian,</hi> and put himſelf a <hi>Club</hi> (he knows the Term which is common among Philoſophers of that Sect) to a <hi>Merchant Adventurer,</hi> whoſe Name was <hi>Thorn,</hi> living near <hi>Strand-Bridge:</hi> Theſe Merchants do generally uſe a Sparing Diet about <hi>July</hi> and <hi>Auguſt,</hi> walk with their <hi>Hands in their Pockets,</hi> and ſuddenly after go a Nutting: With this Maſter he continued ſome time, and in concluſion (being moved by a pious Inclination) entered into the Holy State of Matrimony: But under what Circumſtances he was afterwards, I ſhall forbear to mention, as being unwilling to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect on thoſe Accidents that naturally attend the Order of Nature, and the Fate of Mankind, Poverty and Neceſſity being liable to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man at one time or other of his Life, and he that never feels the ſmart of it, may be reckoned among the happieſt ſort of men in this World: And indeed here muſt I put an end to the more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent part of his Life, and alſo make a bar between the former and the latter; for now he puts on the <hi>Armour</hi> of a bad <hi>Conſcience,</hi> to juſtifie and defend his <hi>worſe Crimes,</hi> and alſo a Vail of Piety, <hi>ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> Hypocriſie, to be thought a Man of great Religion and Vertue in his new Undertakings; For now he reſolves (as his Actions prove) to be <hi>aut Caeſar, aut Nullus,</hi> and to want no Preferment that Crimes can procure.</p>
            <p>And to qualifie him for the Excellence of ſuch Undertakings, he falls in with the then <hi>Presbyterian Congregations</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards with the <hi>Independants,</hi> as himſelf ſays in his Doctrine of <hi>Nativities,</hi> pag. 262. <q>About the 22d year of his Age (he ſays) he was almoſt mad about the Doctrine of Predeſtination, becauſe he could not find in himſelf thoſe ſigns of God's Love and Favour which they told him of; and therefore ſometimes concluded that he was in a ſtate of Damnation.</q> But this Religious Strain did not hold long, for indeed it was too hot to hold; and if you do but obſerve, you will for the moſt part find ſuch <hi>Young Zealots</hi> as he was, are generally more <hi>Whoremongers</hi> than <hi>Divines;</hi> he ſuddenly thinks of hunting for a new Religion, and it muſt be ſuch a one too that muſt ſecure him from the fears of Damnation under his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Crimes and Villanies; and the firſt he met with, and moſt ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to his Humour was the <hi>Family</hi> of <hi>Love, Ranters,</hi> or <hi>Sweet-ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> of <hi>Iſrael; Coppe</hi> at that time being the Head of them, and my Friend <hi>John</hi>'s, <hi>Spiritual Father;</hi> and as the Cant then run, <hi>He begot
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94020:7"/>
him in the Lord;</hi> which was as much as to ſay, He converted him: This was the only fit Faith and Religion that ever my Friend found, for never was <hi>Halter</hi> and <hi>Thief</hi> better matched, than <hi>John</hi> and this <hi>Family</hi> of <hi>Love;</hi> for Lewdneſs, Whoredom and all Vice, were the Principles and Practice of this Zealous Crew, they holding all things in common, from the Purſe to the Placket; now our Friend begins to put himſelf forward, and ſhew his Parts by inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the reſt of the Crew; and to that end, being more than half drunk, at <hi>London-wall</hi> he undertook to preach from that Paſſage in the 11th of <hi>Judges,</hi> and the 1ſt. <hi>ver. And Jephthah was the Son of a Harlot;</hi> a very proper Text for Mr. <hi>John</hi> to diſcourſe to the people, and eſpecially if he doth but conſider how plaguy doubtful his own Birth was (he knows the meaning of it) and recollects the Paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that then occur'd.</p>
            <p>This ſort of <hi>Faith-jobbing</hi> did not content him long, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſome new thing was to be again found out; and to that end, when <hi>Cromwell</hi> came to be <hi>Protector,</hi> he begins to inſinuate at <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall,</hi> in order to make an Intereſt, to dedicate his Book, called the <hi>Doctrine of Nativities</hi> to <hi>Oliver;</hi> to which end he tells how he had been a Sufferer, and loſt his Fortune and Eſtate by the <hi>Royal Party;</hi> and that he was ready to ingage all that he had left to ſerve that Intereſt; but ſomebody cut the Graſs under <hi>John</hi>'s Feet, and no Butter ſtuck upon his Bread at that time, ſo that then he thought it moſt convenient to turn <hi>Book-wright</hi> for a <hi>Spiritual Liveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Protector</hi> going off the Stage, and <hi>Charles</hi> II. coming in, <hi>John</hi> then falls in, Hand and Heart, with that Government; <hi>Turns</hi> Church <hi>of</hi> England <hi>Man,</hi> and it was <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Martyr</hi> at every Word; then he call'd the <hi>Nonconformiſts, Rebels</hi> and <hi>Raſcals,</hi> and rail'd like a Butter whore at them in defence of the Church; and by this way of Inſinuation he was at laſt taken notice of by ſome of thoſe then Red hot Saints, and from <hi>Jewin ſtreet</hi> in 1666. he comes to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> where he did generally appear at the <hi>Abby</hi> once every <hi>Sunday,</hi> to cheat Mankind into a good Opinion of his Sanctity; when to ſay the Truth, it was no more but a <hi>Hypocritical</hi> Paroxiſm, as you will ſee hereafter.</p>
            <p>About the Year 1667. he fell mightily in love with the <hi>Gardiner</hi>'s <hi>Daughter,</hi> who was another Man's Wife at that time, who by Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Converſation, and Amorous Letters, and Copies of Verſes, he perſwades her to leave her Husband Bed, and come and keep him and his Wife company; the ſilly woman complies, and was by his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94020:7"/>
mountain Promiſes deluled, and by the help of <hi>Don John,</hi> under his Wife's Noſe, ſhe humbly conceived in a little time; then he decoy'd her to Mrs. <hi>W</hi>'s, with great Promiſes to take care of her, and viſit her often, but after he had got her out of his own Houſe, he never went near her: This put her into a deep Melancholy, which made Mrs. <hi>W.</hi> ask the reaſon, which when ſhe knew, went to <hi>John,</hi> and acquainted him with the Matter; <hi>Ay,</hi> ſays he, <hi>hath ſhe told it? then let her go like a Whore as ſhe is;</hi> a true <hi>Scorpioniſt.</hi> The poor Woman made hard ſhift to ſubſiſt, and at laſt was brought to Bed; and when ſhe was up again, three Whores (you may gueſs by whom employed) met her in the Evening, and had like to have killed her: After this her <hi>Husband</hi> indicted this Friend of Mine at the Seſſious, for debauching his Wife, and a few days before it was to come to a Tryal, he was murdered privately, and 'tis forty to one but you will gueſs who did it, or at leaſt had a hand in it: <hi>A True Blew Catholick Saint,</hi> and all this time one of our <hi>Church,</hi> and at the <hi>Abby</hi> almoſt every <hi>Sunday. Monſtrum horendum!</hi> Can any man ſleep in peace that has the gaſhly Ghoſt of a murdered man in his mind? or appearing before the Eyes of his wretched reſtleſs Conſcience: It is no wonder to me, to ſee men run and ruſh into the moſt flagitious Crimes in Nature, that have been once fluſht in the <hi>Blood of Mankind,</hi> and what is a leader to it, <hi>Subornation of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury;</hi> two ſuch Crimes, that all Chriſtian Governments have provided the ſevereſt of Laws for their ſevere puniſhments.</p>
            <p>From this time forward for ſome years together, he was ruffling all Mankind, vindicating <hi>Scorpio,</hi> and promiſing us his <hi>Body of Tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tology:</hi> Not to mention any thing of the Two <hi>By-blows</hi> that were at Nurſe in <hi>Tuttle-fields,</hi> where his Friend <hi>Baxter</hi> told me he had been with him divers times; nor the Friendſhip and Intimacy he then contracted with the Trayterous <hi>Popiſh Prieſts,</hi> from whom he learned the Murdering Principles afterward diſcovered in the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Plot, as you may ſee by Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi>'s own Words, in his Animadverſions on <hi>Gadbury</hi>'s Almanack for 1682. his words are theſe, ſpeaking to <hi>John Gadbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>That you and I, upon, or about the 2d of <hi>September</hi> 1689, entring into Diſcourſe, I perceived your Countenance to change; when looking very angrily on me, <hi>you</hi> told me, That you wonde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that I would offer to diſpleaſe the Lords in the <hi>Tower,</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the Lord <hi>Caſtlemain</hi> (then out upon Bail) who deſign'd to advance me in the World, and help me to make my Fortune. To which I replied, That I was not a little ſurprized to hear ſuch
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94020:8"/>
words from <hi>you,</hi> and asked <hi>you</hi> if <hi>you</hi> knew the ground of their diſpleaſure; <hi>you</hi> then replied yes, yes, <hi>you</hi> did; and then falling into a great Paſſion, ſaid, It was becauſe I would not <hi>kill</hi> the King; ſaid <hi>you</hi> to me, I admire at your Ingratitude, that when you could not propoſe to your ſelf any poſſible way of getting out of Priſon, &amp;c. that you ſhould offer to refuſe it; Nay, ſaid <hi>you</hi> to me, I might have done it with all the eaſe in the world, for no manner of hurt could have befallen me: Why, ſaid I, would not Death unavoidably have been the conſequence of it? No, ſaid <hi>you,</hi> for before I was releaſed out of the <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Bench, you</hi> had an exact account from Mrs. <hi>Cellier,</hi> of the Year, Month, Week, Day and Hour I was born in, and the Counteſs of <hi>P.</hi> ordered you to calculate my Nativity; And it is ſo clear, ſaid <hi>you</hi> to me, that you are by all adjudged the Perſon allotted for that bold and da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Enterprize.</q> This is the Atteſtation left by Mr. <hi>Dangerfield;</hi> So that you ſee he is not content to be padling in Blood himſelf, but for perſwading others to engage in thoſe Black Crimes alſo; for which he was taken into cuſtody the 2d of <hi>November, Anno</hi> 1679. And this is the firſt notorious Plot that we find him engaged in againſt the <hi>King, Religion</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> at which time he was certainly a <hi>Papiſt;</hi> he having at, or about that time told a Friend of mine, That under this laſt Conjunction in <hi>Leo,</hi> and its Effects, all <hi>Europe</hi> would be ſubjugated to the <hi>Romiſh See,</hi> and that it was good policy in all wiſe men to turn betimes, and ſo adviſed him. Hence you may be certain, that he who adviſed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, was without doubt of that Perſwaſion himſelf. Yet for all this, he denied it before the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Counſel,</hi> and forſwore it upon the Sacrament, in his <hi>Magna Veritas;</hi> and yet in 1685. I heard him own it; and afterwards he openly profeſt himſelf a <hi>Papiſt.</hi> And after all this <hi>Hypocritical Faith-jobbing,</hi> I hear he is turn'd <hi>Proteſtant</hi> again, and a ſpecial one too, no doubt, and it is indeed, the fifth or ſixth time he hath found it convenient to change his Religion, if ever he had any.</p>
            <p>While he was in Priſon, he ſent his Maid with a Preſent of Plate to Sir <hi>T. D.</hi> to get his Pardon, but he finding the Caſe ſo ſoul, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to be concerned in it; however he trebled the value of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and ſent it to another (now dead) by whoſe means, and ſome <hi>Popiſh</hi> Intereſt, his Pardon was produced: Yet during his Confinement he had accuſed <hi>Dame Cellier</hi> of ſome ſoul Treaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Crimes before the King and Council, which he gave under his Hand; but when ſhe came to be tryed the <hi>Summer</hi> following, in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94020:8"/>
               <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> and he called to juſtifie what he had before ſworn againſt her; He told the <hi>Judge, He did not remember any ſuch thing;</hi> he own'd it was his Hand, but his Memory was bruiſed by being in Priſon, and he could not ſay any thing to the Matter: <hi>A very ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Fellow!</hi> For this and ſome other <hi>Popiſh Services</hi> he received 200 <hi>l.</hi> In the Year 1681. a certain Member of the <hi>Church of Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicea,</hi> that liv'd within a mile and a half of <hi>Strand-Bridge,</hi> and well known to my Friend <hi>J. Gadbury</hi> and my ſelf, for many vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Qualifications, drew up in a Paper certain <hi>Articles,</hi> of ſeveral high and Treaſonable Crimes againſt Sir <hi>T. D.</hi> and then brought theſe to Mr. <hi>Sprigg</hi> in <hi>King-ſtreet, Weſtminſter,</hi> and deſired him to go before a Juſtice of Peace, and make Affidavit of its Truth, but Mr. <hi>Sprigg</hi> deſired a little time to conſider of it; which being gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, away he came to me, and asked my Opinion what he ſhould do in it? I asked him if it was true? he ſaid, No; Why, then ſaid I, do not you by any means oblige a Villain with a Falſe Oath, to rui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny Gentleman's Reputation and Eſtate, and perhaps life too. But, ſaid he, I owe him Money, and am afraid, if I do deny this thing, he will arreſt me. No, ſaid I, never fear that, for this thing of <hi>Subornation</hi> will keep him in awe I dare ingage; and from that time this <hi>Laodicean</hi> did differ with Mr. <hi>Sprigg</hi> for refuſing this hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid thing, and <hi>Knave</hi> and <hi>Villain</hi> were the beſt Words he could give him; and there are ſeveral yet living, that know this Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous thing from Mr. <hi>Sprigg</hi>'s Relation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Year 1681 and 1682. his <hi>Maid</hi> took an occaſion to leave her Maſter (he then being a Widower) I think twice, <hi>Ay,</hi> ſays, he to his Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman, <hi>let her go, ſhe will be glad to come again, when ſhe finds ſhe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not mend her ſelf:</hi> And truly juſt as he ſaid, ſo it fell out; for after ſhe had been gone about three Months, ſhe returned much ſlende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer than ſhe was when ſhe went away, for I ſuppoſe ſhe had been cured of a <hi>Timpany,</hi> or ſome other diſeaſe of the <hi>Bowels;</hi> perhaps ſome <hi>Tumor</hi> or <hi>Excreſcence</hi> in her <hi>Womb,</hi> of which ſhe did very well, and was fit to follow her former Employment again. Now what man of Senſe can doubt his being a <hi>Conjurer,</hi> for how ſhould he know elſe ſhe would come again? he muſt have this from ſome plagny cunning Star, ſuch a one, I ſuppoſe, as he predicted the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> by, in 1686. Ah <hi>John,</hi> did you ever know an <hi>Owl</hi> and a <hi>Sparrowhawk</hi> build both in a Hole? pray where was your <hi>Handmaid church'd</hi> after the cure of the <hi>Timpany</hi> that you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed into her?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:94020:9"/>In the Year 1684. he was frequently converſant with the <hi>Popiſh Prieſts,</hi> and no doubt but he could have given us an account of the fatal Stroke that was given the 2d of <hi>February</hi> following, if he had thought it convenient; <hi>Popery</hi> was his <hi>Darling,</hi> and it muſt be brought in, though the Nation was waſh'd in Blood for its Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment.</p>
            <p>In the Year 1685. he was extremely full of Buſineſs, the Nation being then a Sacrifice to <hi>Popery,</hi> and he as a Servant to the <hi>Idol Prieſts,</hi> did expect a ſhare in the Offerings; it was now time for him to ſhew his early Complyane with the Enemies of <hi>England,</hi> and ſhew early Signs of his Converſion; for it was his <hi>Maxim</hi> to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral at that time, <hi>That none ſhould be preferr'd but</hi> Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, <hi>and ſuch as would be ſo when the King pleaſed,</hi> Ergo, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now it was that he told Mr. <hi>B. That the firſt time he went to Maſs, there were twelve</hi> Engliſh Peers <hi>there at Maſs at the ſame time, and now was the time for him to make his Calling and Election ſure. A pious hopeful Chriſtian!</hi> And the better to pave his way to Prefer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nt, he now undertook the Office of a <hi>Runner,</hi> and an <hi>Informer,</hi> in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to ruine five or ſix Gentlemen in <hi>London,</hi> by a <hi>Scandalum Mag.</hi> for publiſhing Mr. <hi>Dangerfield</hi>'s <hi>Narrative;</hi> this was a bleſſed time. But to ſay the truth, <hi>John</hi> got 20 <hi>per Cent.</hi> by it. And who of <hi>John</hi>'s Perſwaſion would not be a Villain for that Wages? when, for ought he knew, there were half a dozen men to be ruined for it. But no matter for that; were his Father now living, and a <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> he would betray him too, rather than miſs getting the Money; I know his Principle ſo well.</p>
            <p>In 1686. and 1687. Mr. <hi>Bounce</hi> went about like a Roaring Lyon to make Converts for his old <hi>Granny</hi> the <hi>Whore</hi> of <hi>Babylon;</hi> now it was that he told Mr. <hi>B. He muſt be forced to have him to Father</hi> Petre, <hi>and Father</hi> Ellis; thoſe two who he had brought him to before, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not able to convert him. Now it was that he impudently ſaid, <hi>It would never be well till that King laid by Parliaments, and rul'd by his Abſolute Power.</hi> Now it was he ſaid, <hi>The Kings of</hi> England <hi>were not obliged by Law, to take the Coronation Oath;</hi> Reply, <hi>pag.</hi> 8. Now it was he promiſed the <hi>Papiſts, An Eternal Settlement in</hi> England, <hi>and that their Cauſe and Power would be as durable as the Sun,</hi> Epiſtle to his <hi>Almanack<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 1686. But alas, they had nothing to ſay for it, but <hi>Honeſt Jack</hi>'s Word: His Word, What's that worth, when the Nation knows he is a — Now it was that he told us, <hi>There ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y ſuch think as a Plot by the Papiſts, in King</hi> James <hi>the Firſt's Time,</hi> Reply <hi>pag.</hi> 3. which I ſuppoſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> implies a Reaſon why he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94020:9"/>
omitted it in his <hi>Almanack</hi> every Year. Now what think you of my Dark Lanthorn Conjurer, is he not a Seraphick Youth? at this time I can aſſure you he was an <hi>Impudent, Inſolent, openly-profeſs'd Papiſt,</hi> and talk'd both like Knave and Fool. Now it was that he rail'd and rav'd againſt the <hi>Church of England</hi> in defence of <hi>Popery,</hi> as he uſed to do againſt the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> and <hi>Fanaticks,</hi> in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> after <hi>Charles</hi> the Second came in: Now it was that all were Villains and Traytors (in <hi>John</hi>'s Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) that would not ſubmit againſt the Laws to a <hi>Popiſh King,</hi> and give up their Liberties, Eſtates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to Old <hi>Granne Church</hi> again, to maintain Abby Lubbers, and Whoriſh Nuns, <hi>John</hi>'s peculiar Saints; and now it was he wanted to be a Juſtice of Peace.</p>
            <p>In 1688. when the Party began to apprehend a Storm, <hi>Jack</hi>'s Buſineſs was to ſupport them with Promiſes, and apply warm Clouts to their Capacities, while his own trembled like an Apſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaf; ſee his fulſome <hi>Almanack</hi> for that Year. Now it was he gave a written Paper out among the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> wherein were Words to this purport, the Prince being then coming; <hi>He hoped to ſee him, and his Great men with him, brought to make Speeches at</hi> Tower-hill <hi>and</hi> Tyburn: you ſee Honeſt <hi>John</hi> was then for making thorough Work; whoever affronted him, or <hi>Granne Church</hi> at that time, he ſcorn'd to give himſelf the trouble to contend, or talk out his Thoughts to them, or convert them, but throw a <hi>Halter,</hi> a <hi>Hatchet,</hi> or a <hi>Gallows</hi> at them, and then their Work was done, and they were certainly dead in Law; What! Affront <hi>Jack,</hi> or his Church!</p>
            <p>In 1689. <hi>John</hi> was come to his <hi>Ne plus Ultra</hi> in <hi>Popery,</hi> and for a long time never ſaid his Prayers, becauſe he did not know what ſort of them he ſhould take up with next; for he reſolves to go to Heaven by no other Religion than that which is in faſhion; no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter if it be <hi>Mahumetiſm,</hi> that will do according to <hi>John</hi>'s Notion in his <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to his <hi>Almanack,</hi> 1682. where he ſays, <hi>That God always ſends Kings of that Religion which he expects thoſe Nations to be of, where they govern:</hi> This is a very honeſt Fellow, he came <hi>raw</hi> into the World, and will never go roaſted out for <hi>Religion,</hi> I will paſs my word for him.</p>
            <p>In 1690. about <hi>June, John</hi> was catch'd at the <hi>Poſt-Office,</hi> in ſending a Bundle of Treaſon to ſome of his <hi>Popiſh</hi> Friends, in which was one of King <hi>James's Declarations,</hi> a <hi>Treaſonable Copy of Verſes</hi> againſt the King and Queen, which he promiſed his Friend, ſhould be printed in a ſhort time; but above all, a moſt <hi>Villanous
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94020:10"/>
Letter</hi> againſt the <hi>Government,</hi> in which he aſſured his Friend, that King <hi>J</hi>'s <hi>Declarations</hi> were ſet up on all the <hi>Church Doors</hi> in <hi>Devon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire</hi> and <hi>Cornwall,</hi> and that they had agreed with the <hi>French</hi> King to take off all their <hi>Tin</hi> at a certain rate, and they had all declared for King <hi>James;</hi> and to uſe his own Words for it, he ſaid, <hi>King</hi> J's <hi>Intereſt was like a Cart overthrowed, and therefore they muſt get a conſiderable help to ſet it upright on its Wheels again, and then drive on as before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I would ask him if this Rebellious Principle is agreeable to his old <hi>N iſey Doctrine of Non-reſiſtance,</hi> when he asks, what is <hi>Paſſive Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> turned into, <hi>bearding, upbraiding,</hi> and <hi>dethroning</hi> of Kings, <hi>Rep.</hi> pag. 21. But at that time <hi>John</hi> was a <hi>Popiſh</hi> Caſuiſt to defend a baſe and Villanous Cauſe, the ſhaven Crowns, and their Dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baked Gods; the very Treaſon that he was taken in that Year, in the <hi>Late bloody Reigns</hi> would have hang'd any man: The D. of <hi>Monmouths</hi> Declaration took away <hi>Will. Diſney</hi>'s Life; and Collonel <hi>Sidney</hi> died for <hi>publiſhing a Book in his Study;</hi> Mr. <hi>Colledge</hi> for car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying a Regiment of men in a Portmanteau to ſeiſe the King at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford;</hi> but <hi>John</hi> met with a more merciful Government, and a better Fate, but how he deſerved it, I will leave you to judge.</p>
            <p>In 1691. his time was employed in ſupporting the Party, and giving them aſſurances of their old Maſter's Return, and this by the power of the Stars. In the end of 1688. he did aſſure them he would be here again by <hi>Chriſtmas,</hi> or to uſe his own words for it, For a <hi>New-years-Gift;</hi> that failing, he engaged he would be here at fartheſt, by <hi>Eaſter,</hi> in 1689. but that alſo failing; and then he was certain he would not fail of being here by <hi>Michaelmas,</hi> and then he put them off till <hi>Eaſter</hi> 1690. and becauſe he would be ſure of it then, he was in a Plot himſelf to reſtore him; juſt like Young <hi>Noſtradamus,</hi> they tell of, who predicted the burning of a City, and rather than have his Prophecy want ſucceſs, he fired it himſelf, for which he was hang'd.</p>
            <p>In 1692. he had a freſh Ferment in his Conſcience about Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and having not confidence to go to the Abby where he uſed to go, when he was a ſuppoſed <hi>Proteſtant</hi> before, I hear he comes now to St. <hi>Margaret</hi>'s Church as a Proteſtant, and with abundance of Devotion, you may be ſure; where he certainly lies <hi>purdue,</hi> to watch for another Opportunity to change his Religion, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſhape his Conſcience according to the next New Cut of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94020:10"/>
Faith that he finds ſuitable to his Advantage and Intereſt, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the two main Arguments of his Religion and Piety; and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he is again turned a <hi>Mungrel Proteſtant of the</hi> Church <hi>of</hi> England, I have heard very lately, that he hath trumpt up a New Argument, to encourage the Papiſts, and their Accomplices to expect their Old Maſter next Year, 1694. and that is from the MC <hi>ad</hi> ☌ ♃: but the Lord help his Ignorance and his Folly, and pity thoſe that are deluded by him, for that Direction will not come up before he is almoſt 69 years of Age, in the year 1702. and for the MC. <hi>ad</hi> 
               <g ref="char:trine">△</g> ☉ that comes up not till 1709. ſo great is his Ignorance and Confidence, to comfort the Party with Lies and Juggles.</p>
            <p>Thus I have brought this worthy Gentleman to the 65th Year of his Age, and very fairly given you the Account of his Life, as to thoſe things I treat of, and do really think I have not done him any Injury in relating Matter of Fact; if I am any ways out, or amiſs, it is only in being ſhort, and not relating his Crimes to the height they were acted by their Author; and therefore I had rather mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly ſcreen his Villanies with a deficiency in Relation of them, than to abound in their Hiſtory at this time; and this the rather, becauſe the very Glimpſe of them in this ſhort Account, will give him ſo foul, and ſo black a Character, that all men of Honeſty and Honour will deteſt his Principles, and conclude him to be the greateſt — in the world. What will you ſay to him that enticeth away and ſteals his Neighbour's Dog? Why, you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not call him leſs than Thief; but then what will you judge him to be, that by <hi>Amorous Letters, Copies of Verſes,</hi> and <hi>Vocal Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,</hi> enticeth away his <hi>Neighbour's Wife,</hi> takes her to his Houſe, gets her with Child, and then kicks her out of Doors again, to the mercy of the wide world, and the fury of her Husband, not to ſpeak a word of the Murther of Mr. G. and theſe are ſo well known, that there are many in Town acquainted with each Particular; and indeed I know ſomething of the matter my ſelf, having had the Honour to ſee her at his Houſe at that time.</p>
            <p>What will you think of him that hunts for a New <hi>Faith,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times once a Year, but for the moſt part, once <hi>every Seven Years?</hi> What will you think of him that was in a Plot to <hi>murther</hi> the <hi>King</hi> he always pretented to ſupport? what think you of him that was in another Plot, to <hi>murther</hi> and <hi>dethrone</hi> that <hi>King</hi> that had before pardoned him, and forgave all his Villanies and Treaſons againſt him?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:94020:11"/>What will you think of him that railed and raved at the <hi>Royal Party</hi> in 1657. that railed at the <hi>Fanaticks</hi> from 1660. forwards; that railed at the Church of <hi>England</hi> in defence of Popery, in the</p>
            <p>Year 1687. and now curſeth his own <hi>Stars</hi> that he wants power to be a greater — than he is.</p>
            <p>What think you of him that would have ſuborned a man to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve ſworn Crimes againſt a <hi>Gentleman,</hi> even to <hi>Life, Liberty</hi> and <hi>Estate?</hi> This is ſuch a <hi>Villany,</hi> that none but ſuch who are perjured them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, would ever attempt; <hi>Suborners of Perjury!</hi> why they are worſe than <hi>Highway-men</hi> and <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſe-breakers;</hi> for we may be ſafe from one ſort by ſtrong Doors and Walls, and from the other by ſtaying at home; But who can be ſafe againſt falſe <hi>Oaths?</hi> who can be ſafe when two or three conſpire together, and are willing to take a Falſe <hi>Oath</hi> at the price of their own Damnation and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Ruin: What ſhall we ſay? when a Man hath his Life ſnatched from him, by the Falſe <hi>Oaths</hi> of two <hi>perjured Villains,</hi> and dies an Ignominious Death, for a Baſe and Scandalous Crime that he was never guilty of! (The Lord remember the ſufferings of the people in the <hi>Late Bloody Reigns.</hi>) Perjury is ſuch a Crime, that next to Murther, our <hi>Lawgivers</hi> have thought fit to make a ſevere Act for the puniſhment of ſuch Offenders; and yet you ſee when Malice rides abroad <hi>Rampant,</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> ſtays at home, it is no hard thing to find a certain Saint, that uſed to go with abundance of Devotion to the <hi>Abby,</hi> who is willing to undergo not only the <hi>Drudgery</hi> of <hi>Swearing,</hi> but Swearing falſly, or at leaſtwiſe to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade others to do it, which if there is any difference, is the worſt Crime of the two; and I doubt not but every one who is willing to perſwade others to ſuch Offences, are ready to do it themſelves, or elſe have been guilty of the ſame Crimes formerly. Who can have the impudence to look God or Man in the Face, without bluſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or a dejected Countenance, when he knows his Soul is loaded with ſuch a horrid Villany, and his Conſcience tells him every moment, that he deſerves the puniſhment due to ſo heinous a thing; or elſe on his Knees he ought to confeſs it, and beg the <hi>Gentleman</hi>'s Pardon, if he is not paſt Grace and Repentance.</p>
            <p>And ſo I come to conſider a <hi>Pamphlet</hi> lately ſent forth into the World without a Name, as if the Author of it was either afraid or aſham'd to own what he had done; or elſe by reaſon of other Crimes, he thought his Name, inſtead of making his Book ſell, might have damn'd it to a perpetual oblivion and have ſaved us the labour of reading it; <hi>Ex pede Hercules;</hi> by the Man you may know
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94020:11"/>
the Matter; and you may be certain that <hi>J. G.</hi> can as ſoon eat that Paper, as write a Treatiſe without his Two <hi>Martyrs</hi> in it; juſt like <hi>Roger</hi> wedded to <hi>Forty One.</hi> And tho it comes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Author's Name in the Title Page, yet I can without the help of the Stars, tell it came out of <hi>Brick-Court,</hi> and that <hi>John Gadbury</hi> is the Author of it; which he calls <hi>Merlini Liberati Errata;</hi> which I will conſider, and give an Anſwer to his material Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons therein alledged againſt me; and do aſſure him, that as I have already made him appear a <hi>Knave,</hi> ſo I will ſhew the World he is alſo a <hi>Fool,</hi> eſpecially in that <hi>Profeſſion</hi> he pretends to, which is the <hi>Art</hi> of <hi>Aſtrology;</hi> and likewiſe how ſilly, as well as falſe, the moſt part of his Objections are, paſſing by his wittyc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſms, as well as his Reflections, being ſenſible that the beſt of Authors, nay, the Word of God too, hath been defamed and abuſed by the Witty <hi>Jeſts,</hi> &amp;c. of Debauched Men; and by ſome in particular, of <hi>J. G.</hi>'s Acquaintance that I could name.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb facs="tcp:94020:12"/>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:94020:12"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO HIS Idle PAMPHLET.</head>
            <p>IN his Title Page I perceive he is an earneſt Honourer of his <hi>King,</hi> &amp;c. I am glad to hear of ſuch a Reformation, for it is not three years ſince he was accus'd of being in a Plot to <hi>dethrone</hi> and <hi>murther</hi> the <hi>King;</hi> and to this day he cannot in conſcience take the Oaths to Their <hi>Majeſties,</hi> and yet an earneſt Honourer of the King, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It would be convenient, I think, to ask him, <hi>What King?</hi> for I am ſure our King is not his, if he cannot take an Oath to be true to Him.</p>
            <p>In his Epiſtle to the Reader, he complains of my <hi>Bruitiſh Bawl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and <hi>Beaſtly Language,</hi> which is needleſs (if true) ſeeing he pretends to be my Maſter; having taught me one by his <hi>Bouncing Empty Writings,</hi> and the other by his <hi>Debauched</hi> and <hi>Beaſt-like Life</hi> and <hi>Converſation.</hi> In the very next Words he takes care of the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State;</hi> meaning, I judge, that of <hi>France;</hi> for a <hi>Papiſt</hi> can never intend the <hi>Church of England;</hi> if he doth, and deſigns what he ſays, he is damn'd by his own Principles; but you may ſee he hath undertaken to patch up the Cauſe, and therefore let it be ſo; and for his two Martyrs, I refer my Reader to <hi>M. G. Ludlow</hi>'s Letter for the one, and to the <hi>Cruelties</hi> of the <hi>Star-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> (eſpecially Dr. <hi>Layton</hi>'s Caſe) for the other; for I have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe to do, than to ſpend my precious Time about ſuch things as are not to my preſent Purpoſe. And at laſt of all, he calls out to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> for help; one would think he might call to his own <hi>Church,</hi> if he knew which it was, which I doubt he
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94020:13"/>
doth not, after all this choping and changing of his Religions; for he always ſerves his God in the neweſt Faſhion; and ſo I come to the Matter it ſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 6. The firſt thing he falls foul on ſhews the Fellow to be <hi>top-full of Malice;</hi> and what little things muſt ſerve him to make a noiſe with in my <hi>Epiſtle;</hi> I ſaid, <hi>This little Book will run the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thorough;</hi> but that way did not pleaſe him, it ſeems, to expreſs it; and therefore after a great deal of noiſey ſtuff, he puts me, as he thinks, in a better way, to ſay this little Book ſhall run tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the Nation; a very Learned Diſtinction, and after his uſual Banter, he adviſeth the Nation to be provided of good <hi>Surgeons,</hi> I ſuppoſe he means <hi>Cloath-Surgeons,</hi> alias, <hi>Srand-lane Garret-men:</hi> As for the Cauſe of our <hi>Difference</hi> mentioned in that Page, I ſhall take notice in another Place, more proper than this, and alſo ſet the <hi>Goad</hi> and the <hi>Awl</hi> he mentions there againſt his <hi>Bodkin</hi> and <hi>Needle,</hi> and let his Sixfooted-ſtraglers take which they pleaſe to contend for their Maſter's Honeſty, when he was ſaving the Rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; in the ſame Page he quarrels becauſe I ſay, there were no material <hi>Rays</hi> and <hi>Poſitions,</hi> &amp;c. and then the <hi>Blockhead</hi> with his <hi>Rumbling Nonſenſe,</hi> draws an Inference, as if I ſaid there were no <hi>Rays</hi> and <hi>Poſitions.</hi> I ſaid there were no <hi>Rays</hi> material, to give any kind of remarkable things in the <hi>Air,</hi> or <hi>Mundane Affairs;</hi> but our <hi>Popiſh-Jugler</hi> is for any thing, ſo he can but make a noiſe: <hi>Oh the Impudence of the Fellow!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 7th. In <hi>February.</hi> I wonder he ſhould be ſo impudent to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny there was a <hi>Popiſh Plot</hi> going on in <hi>February,</hi> according as I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted it, from the preceeding Conjunction of <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Saturn,</hi> in the <hi>Gadburian Sign;</hi> when he knows he himſelf (like an ill man) was taken a few Months afterwards, as he was ſending <hi>Treaſonable Letters, Popiſh Declarations,</hi> &amp;c. to his <hi>Popiſh Conſpirators,</hi> to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broil the King and Government; here it is plain the Deſign was then going on, or elſe I muſt conclude <hi>John</hi> made a <hi>Plot</hi> himſelf, on purpoſe to verifie my Prediction, and now takes this Opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to let the World know how kind he was to me; 'tis ſtrange that <hi>Nature,</hi> his <hi>Stars,</hi> his <hi>Parents,</hi> and his <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> ſhould all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire to compleat this Monſter of <hi>Mankind;</hi> he was <hi>doubtfully begot, painfully b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>viſhly bred, whoriſhly vicious, impudently lives,</hi> and doubtleſs will as <hi>knaviſhly die;</hi> And then for the Story of the <hi>Stars</hi> giving. I will talk with him by and by. <hi>Pag.</hi> 7. In <hi>March</hi> he tells me, <hi>I mention a great Congreſs of the Planets in Piſces,</hi> which is a moſt <hi>notorious Falſhood:</hi> My words are theſe, <hi>We here find no leſs
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94020:13"/>
than ſix of the Seven Planets in Watery Signs,</hi> &amp;c and at that time they were all in <hi>Watery Signs,</hi> except <hi>Mars,</hi> and not one Word of a <hi>Congreſs</hi> there, till you come to the next <hi>Paragraph,</hi> where the word <hi>Congreſs</hi> is uſed, and I ſuppoſe not improperly, when there are <hi>Five Planets</hi> in one <hi>Sign; Ah my</hi> Popiſh <hi>Apoſtate! thou haſt been always gifted with Lying and Treaſon, ever ſince you gave over going to the</hi> Abby Church.</p>
            <p>Pag. 8. <hi>April.</hi> He makes a great noiſe about the Word <hi>give;</hi> I having ſaid, <hi>The</hi> Planets <hi>give ſuch, and ſuch things;</hi> methinks the Word may do well enough, tho the <hi>Stars</hi> have no hands: What think you <hi>John?</hi> We give a man a good Word, Why hath the Tongue Hands? You gave the Wench a <hi>Clap,</hi> What hath your Belly Hands? I <hi>give</hi> my conſent, Prethe how ſhall this be done? perhaps I go to do it, Hath my Feet Hands? my Brain contrives it, Hath that Hands? at laſt my Tongue actually doth it, and yet no Hands; ſo that we ſhall ſet the Members together by the ears, who it is that gives this Conſent, and this may be done by a man that hath no Hands: Well, but I am condemned for a <hi>Fool</hi> and <hi>Blockhead,</hi> to uſe it, and that it is a very improper word: Let it be ſo, I will find a Companion preſently: There was a <hi>Sorry empty Treatiſe</hi> a few years ſince, wri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap> by an <hi>Impudent Fellow</hi> in <hi>Brick-Court,</hi> and called a <hi>Collection of Nativities,</hi> in which he printed a hundred <hi>Aphoriſms;</hi> and no leſs than ſeven of thoſe <hi>Aphoriſms</hi> have the very ſame word, and juſt ſo applied; as it is by me, as in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor.</hi> 13. <hi>Fixed Stars on the Angles of a Nativity,</hi> give <hi>the Native eminent honour,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Apho.</hi> 22. again gives the <hi>Native,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Apho.</hi> 50 ♄ and the ☉ in the Second, <hi>give</hi> the <hi>Native</hi> an <hi>Eſtate. Apho.</hi> 67. ☿ In the Houſes of ♄ <hi>gives</hi> an Excellent Underſtanding; and ſo in the 68. and 82 <hi>Aph.</hi> It ſeems when that <hi>Fellow</hi> writ theſe <hi>Aphoriſms,</hi> this was a very good and proper way to expreſs things, but now <hi>Jack,</hi> and the way of expreſſing things are chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. <hi>Well, what ſay you; are you and I Brother-Blockheads or not?</hi> remember the old Adage, <hi>Turpe eſt Doctori cum culpa re darguit ipſum;</hi> what! correct me, <hi>Jack,</hi> and guilty thy ſelf of the very ſame Crime? and indeed it is ſo in moſt of the reſt, if I had but time to examine all thy old Nonſenſe; thou haſt lay ſo long by <hi>Inops men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> that thou art really mad thy ſelf, and I fear thou muſt be ſent to the Colledge in <hi>Moor-fields,</hi> to have thy Senſes reſtored, and thy Memory too, if poſſible: St. <hi>Paul</hi> and you, ſeem to be paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel in your Caſes, but differ in the Terms; for <hi>Feſtus</hi> told him, <hi>That much Learning had made him mad;</hi> but that is none of your Crime; a great deal of <hi>Knavery</hi> and <hi>Impudence</hi> makes you ſo, with the want of the other.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:94020:14"/>Pag. 8. <hi>May. Indeed</hi> John <hi>you fib,</hi> for when that <hi>Almanack</hi> was writ, there was no War in <hi>Ireland,</hi> for your Maſter had not been long landed then, <hi>but there were Wars and Confuſions too;</hi> yet 'tis no matter, I muſt allow my Friend the uſe of his Talent, Lying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It ſeems <hi>Mercury</hi> hath affronted him, or elſe I have, for uſing the young Gentleman's Name; for he ſays, <hi>That</hi> Merlin <hi>is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd by the power of</hi> Mercury, <hi>to utter Lies, as Honeſt</hi> J. G. <hi>was to go to Maſs in</hi> 1686. <hi>or to get his Maid with Child in</hi> 1681. And now I muſt ſhew my Parts in teaching my Maſter, for here he asks me a Learned Queſtion, <hi>How</hi> ☿ <hi>in</hi> Taurus <hi>comes to concern</hi> Ireland <hi>and</hi> France? Why I will tell you <hi>John,</hi> becauſe you are a <hi>Friend,</hi> and becauſe I would willingly keep your Friendſhip; <hi>All Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries do ſuffer, and are concern'd for Good or Ill, according as the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> Nativities <hi>are affected or afflicted, not that I reject the Radical Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of that Country, if it can be had:</hi> And now I think on't, <hi>Pray what</hi> Direction <hi>had</hi> Jamaica <hi>at the time of its</hi> Earthquake, <hi>by the Nonſenſical</hi> Table <hi>of</hi> Directions <hi>that you bubbled thoſe Gentlemen into a belief of? what muſt we ſay, was its</hi> Nativity <hi>falſe, or the</hi> Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <hi>falſe? or did not</hi> J. G. <hi>know how to work them true? which is moſt likely, for he is a very Ignorant Fellow, and alſo very Impudent, or elſe he would be aſham'd of this, as well as of his</hi> Prediction, That Dr. <hi>Oats</hi> ſhould ſtand in the Pillory every year on certain days, and this as long as he liv'd; <hi>but he hath liv'd to ſee himſelf prov'd</hi> Fool <hi>and</hi> Lyar.</p>
            <p>Pag. 9. <hi>June.</hi> Here our <hi>Popiſh Juggler</hi> would be nibling at ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, if he knew what, but it is not a ruſh matter, ſo it makes a noiſe, whether it is to the purpoſe or not; his <hi>Noiſie Objections</hi> are ſo ſilly, that I do not think it worth my Anſwer, for every Reader may eaſily ſee both his Folly, and his Malice: But for a Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of his Skill in <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> I will here relate a ſhort Story of his Confidence in one of his groundleſs <hi>Predictions,</hi> about his Friend Mr. <hi>Lloyd</hi> of <hi>Wales; The poor Gentleman having lain ſome time ill of a</hi> Hectick, <hi>was at laſt given over by his Doctors, but he was unwilling to take the</hi> Sentence of Death <hi>from them contentedly, till he had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted his Friend</hi> Gadbury <hi>with what they ſaid, and to requeſt his O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion about his</hi> Life <hi>or</hi> Death, <hi>and ſo writes him a Letter, and ſent it to him by the Poſt; which being done, his Friends prevailed with him to make his Will, which he did, in which be gave</hi> J. G. 40 <hi>Shillings for his Judgment on his Caſe; ſo Mr.</hi> G. <hi>writes his Anſwer, and told him, That his Doctors were Fools, and did not underſtand either his</hi> Caſe, <hi>or their own</hi> Buſineſs; <hi>and alſo aſſur'd him upon the</hi> Reputation <hi>of a</hi> Brick-Court
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:94020:14"/>
Juggler, <hi>that he would live two years, and ſome few Months, and of this he was certain; ſo away went the</hi> Epiſtle; <hi>but before it came to hand, his Friend was dead; and the Copy of his Letter is now in Town, in a</hi> Phyſician's <hi>hand, who told me the Story, and perhaps it may be printed for the uſe of him and his</hi> Friends. Now pray tell me what is <hi>J. G</hi>'s <hi>Credit</hi> and <hi>Reputation</hi> worth in <hi>Aſtrology?</hi> for he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured him on his <hi>Reputation,</hi> &amp;c. but I can tell him, he is far better at <hi>Faith-Hunting,</hi> than at reading a Lecture on the <hi>Effects</hi> of the <hi>Stars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pag. 9. On <hi>July.</hi> Here our <hi>Paraphraſtical Coxcomb</hi> would be wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a Comment on he knows not what, and repeats my words a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the <hi>two Lights being in a Mundane Parallel with</hi> Jupiter, and tells his Reader the Reaſon why it cannot be ſo, and that is becauſe the <hi>Lunation</hi> did not fall in <hi>Cancer,</hi> but <hi>Leo;</hi> Ha, ha, he! Did e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Soul hear ſuch Ignorance and Nonſenſe, ſet off with ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent a Flouriſh; and I am certain he knows not what a Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dane Parallel is, nor how to work it; and yet this is the Fellow that ſets up for my Maſter; but Ignorance ſeldom goes without Confidence and Lying; and this being proved falſe, all the reſt he ſays on that Month is of the ſame Stamp, which he had by the help of his old Friend, the Father of Lies.</p>
            <p>Pag. 10. In <hi>September.</hi> Here he chargeth me with Lying; he might indeed with a Miſtake; for the Moon did apply firſt to the <hi>Sextile</hi> of <hi>Saturn;</hi> I own that, but it was a Miſtake, and no deſign to do it; but I ſhall be even with him by and by, and I ſuppoſe he knows I will.</p>
            <p>Pag. 9. In <hi>October.</hi> He quarrels with ſomething, but what he cannot tell: I do ſay, <hi>That there were five violent Lunations, and moſt of them in</hi> Libra: It is true, What would my Popiſh Prophet be at, I wonder? there was one on <hi>September</hi> 15. one on <hi>Septem.</hi> 22. a third on <hi>Septem.</hi> 30th. and a Fourth on <hi>October</hi> the 8th. and all theſe were in <hi>Libra,</hi> and all of them violent; therefore the moſt of them were there, as I ſaid before, which is the very thing he carps at; but any thing to make a noiſe with; be ſure the emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Cask makes the greateſt ſound; Why doth not he clear that thing to the world, that I have charg'd upon him, about the MC. to the <hi>Body of Saturn</hi> in his own <hi>Nativity,</hi> that came up, as he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, in the Year 1670. and is a moſt ruinous Direction, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his own Rule, pag. 189. in <hi>Doc.</hi> of <hi>Nativ.</hi> and yet gave him nothing but Grandeur, contrary to its Nature, and his Rule; then it was <hi>every one pull'd in his horns at the daſh of his Pen, not da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94020:15"/>
to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ep out in their own vindication:</hi> Is it ſo now too? I think not.</p>
            <p>Pag. 9th. In <hi>Novem.</hi> Here the word <hi>Wretched</hi> affects him; I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it is becauſe the word beſt ſuits his Inclinations, for he is a <hi>Wretched Fellow,</hi> as you may ſee by the <hi>Actions of his wretched Life,</hi> that precede this Part.</p>
            <p>Pag. 11. <hi>December.</hi> In his witty Harangue on this Month, he firſt makes a Puppet of his own, and then ſets it up and laughs at it; it is he indeed that makes the Nonſenſe; I do quote theſe words, <hi>Significat bellum, eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nem ſarguinis, ac mult<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tudinem Febri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> and do ſay the <hi>French</hi> King would feel its Effects; for a Prince may ſuffer by the loſs and deſtruction of his People, as well as in his own Perſon; ſo after he hath in his way ridicul'd, theſe things, he condemns our poor <hi>Merlin</hi> for a very ſilly ignorant Fellow, and gives the Chair to our Blackthumb'd <hi>Merlin,</hi> and then I am ſure he will chuſe a couple of Lowſy <hi>Strand lane</hi> Centinels with Bodkins in their hands, and a Caſe of Needles by their ſides to be his Guard, and <hi>Verax</hi> in <hi>Brick Court</hi> is to be the Right-hand man; ſo now I think we are all fitted with Places, and being provided, I hope we ſhall be contented, and live lovingly as we uſed to do; and ſo I come to the end of his Opinion on my Twelve Months; and now to ſhew you he is a very ſilly ignorant impudent Fellow, I will give him a home-thruſt at once, and expoſe him to the world, tho I think I cannot make him more notorious than he is; yet I will give my Bodkin-Prophet a Glimps of his Skill, which I am ſure he cares nor to hear. In his <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to that <hi>Ephemerides</hi> that he ſtole from <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cker,</hi> he tells Sir <hi>Frech. Holles;</hi> he ſhould live ſome Decades of years; Firſt here's his Impudence, he affirms he ſhould live ſome years; ſecondly his Ignorance, the Gentleman di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed within Six Months after: Is not this a very ſine <hi>Aſtrologer,</hi> and fit to be a Corrector of others? In his own <hi>Nativity</hi> he tells us he paſſed the <hi>MC.</hi> to the Body of <hi>Saturn</hi> 1670. and gave h m no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing according to its Nature. In the <hi>Nativity</hi> of the Princeſs R yal <hi>Collect. Genitur.</hi> pag. 20. he ſays ſhe married on the <hi>Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> to the Body of <hi>Mars,</hi> and yet he ſends Biſhop <hi>Laud</hi> to the Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er on the very ſame Direction, <hi>pag</hi> 90. of the Collect: And he kills <hi>Charles Guſtavus,</hi> King of <hi>Sweden</hi> on the <hi>MC.</hi> to the Body of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn,</hi> which in his own gave nothing at all. Certainly whoever reads theſe Contradictions, muſt judge <hi>Aſtrology</hi> a very idle Study, or elſe our ſuppoſedly Learned <hi>Thimble Conjurer</hi> to be a very <hi>Ignorant Fellow.</hi> How <hi>John!</hi> you my Maſter, and guilty of this Nonſenſe!
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94020:15"/>
My Maſter was no <hi>Faith-hunter,</hi> but a Man of a ſteady Reputation, one that underſtood <hi>Astrology</hi> better than this, and how to teach it better than you do: Before you quarrel with me in point of <hi>Art,</hi> I challenge you to make theſe Things clear to the World, in an <hi>Aſtroligical</hi> way, which if you do not, you muſt expect to hear from me about them another time. You the <hi>Top-man,</hi> and <hi>Bell-weather</hi> of the whole <hi>Society</hi> of <hi>Aſtrologers!</hi> Are not you a fine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation to your <hi>Profeſſion?</hi> you ſhall have the Chair, but it ſhall be to ſh — in, not to read <hi>Astrology,</hi> unleſs it is a Nonſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal one.</p>
            <p>Pag. 12th. On the <hi>Winter-Quarter.</hi> Here he ſhews himſelf in his True Colours, and to any one that underſtands what a Mundane Parallel is, he will ſoon appear to be what he really is, a Malicious ſilly Fellow; and therefore I will not ſpend time about this, for it anſwers it ſelf, and doth not want mine.</p>
            <p>Pag. 12. On the <hi>Spring-Quarter:</hi> Here my <hi>Thimbletenian</hi> doth charge a notorious<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie upon me; for he ſays that 24 of ♐ aſcends, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> when I ſay 19 of VS doth; pray you that underſtand how to ſet a Figure, enter the Column of Time from Noon, with 15h. 25m. and ſee if the 24th <hi>Degree</hi> of ♏ will not be on the Tenth Houſe, and 19 of <hi>Capricorn</hi> aſcending; if ſo, What doth the <hi>Fellow</hi> make a noiſe about? you ſee he ſticks a Feather in his own Cap, and laughs at his own Folly; for he ſays himſelf, that I give the Ingreſs at 15 h. 25 m. <hi>PM.</hi> and for my ſaying there may be a miſtake of a Sign, two or three in the Aſcendant, when Signs of ſhort Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion riſe in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> is no ſtrange thing; for Operations of that nature being wrought by divers Tables, will differ one or two Hours in time, perhaps more; and it is well known to all Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders to <hi>Aſtrology,</hi> that ♒ ♓ ♈ and ♉ are but 4 hours aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and two of thoſe Signs but 50 Minutes a piece, which proves what I ſay; and ſo he goes on to ridicule me for <hi>Mundane A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects</hi> and <hi>Parallels,</hi> which I am ſure he does not underſtand: And now pray do but obſerve the <hi>Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Impudence</hi> of this <hi>Fellow</hi> that pretends to correct me, that am more true and exact than himſelf.</p>
            <p>In his own <hi>Popiſh Almanack,</hi> pag. 4th. He ſays that the ☉ enters ♈, no <hi>March</hi> the 9th at 6 Hours, 42 Min. after-noon 1693. and how he will prove this, ſeems ſtrange to me, without ſome <hi>Popiſh</hi> Miracle; for in his <hi>Almanack</hi> the <hi>Sun</hi> at Noon, wants 16 Min. to enter <hi>Aries,</hi> which gives in time 6 Hours and 30 Min. which falls ſhort of 6. 42. and therefore if you examine <hi>Shakerly</hi>'s Tables, the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:94020:16"/>
Sun by them enters ♈ at 7 hours 10m. <hi>PM.</hi> and theſe are the Tables which he pretends to go by. Hence it is plain he hath impudently impos'd a time upon us, not agreeable to his own <hi>Almanack,</hi> nor the Tables he pretends to, which ſhews him both ignorant and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident. He underſtand the <hi>Stars!</hi> he knows better how to cuck-cold his Wife, and lie with his Maid (as he call'd her) than to work any <hi>Mathematical Operation:</hi> The <hi>Fellow</hi> is certainly mad, and how it came to paſs I am not certain, unleſs his <hi>Prieſts</hi> made him ſo when he was a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> or that he hath taken a <hi>Frenzy</hi> by Contacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in lying by his Mad Wife; for in 1686. or 87. for the lucre of a little Money, he married a Woman that was really mad, and ſo ſhe is ſtill, and a <hi>Papiſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pag. 14. On the <hi>Summer Quarter,</hi> he here carries on the Rattle as before, and the principal thing is to prove my Figure falſe, and wittily objects at my Saying, <hi>where Armies are in the Field;</hi> and asks me, <hi>If ever I knew Armies in a Houſe?</hi> a very wiſe Queſtion; but I ſhall anſwer my <hi>Popiſh Laplander,</hi> with an Examen of his moſt erronious Calculation, for the <hi>Summer</hi> Ingreſs, 1693. which he tells us, <hi>Is at</hi> 8 <hi>hours</hi> 48 <hi>Min.</hi> PM. June 10th. Now if you will but work that Ingreſs by <hi>Shakerly</hi>'s Tables, you ſhall find that it is at 43 Min. paſt 9. differing almoſt an hour in time from his, and this from them Tables that he pretends to work by: and I hope his Worſhip will allow that an hour in time, makes a great alteration in a Figure of the Twelve Houſes. What think you now of my Corrector, is he ignorant or impudent? I judge it was from ſuch Rules and Grounds he promiſed the <hi>Papiſts, That</hi> Popery <hi>ſhould continue in</hi> England <hi>for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pag. 14. In the <hi>Autumn Quarter;</hi> that is to ſay; in his Dialect, <hi>Cucumber-Time,</hi> here he is upon the old Rumble again, and as true as the former: <hi>But prithee</hi> John, <hi>Why ſhall I not be true to my Wife, if I mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry?</hi> Here you might have forborn that eſpecially, when you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how you uſed your firſt Wife; Take one into the Houſe, and get her with Child under her Noſe; <hi>What do you mean by being juſt? it is not in your Nature; you were never juſt to God nor man,</hi> Ergo <hi>not to your Wife.</hi> And for my coining of falſe Books, that charge lieth at your Door, not mine: And let me tell you, I have begun to publiſh a Doctrine that ſhall ſtand when you and I are gone; but I will take care to give the World an account of what you have writ, and that very ſpeedily too. But you, Mr. <hi>John,</hi> would do well to have your Calculations done better next year, for at the <hi>Winter</hi> Ingreſs, by the Suns place, it is at three quarters paſt 12 at
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:94020:16"/>
Night; and <hi>Shakerly</hi> at half an hour paſt one; but an hour is a ſmall matter in <hi>John</hi>'s Calculations.</p>
            <p>Pag. 15. Of the Eclipſes. I will anſwer the firſt in your own <hi>Almanack</hi> for 1693. pag. 4. You ſay the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> will be eclipſed near out 4 in the Morning, and yet in <hi>January</hi> you ſay the full Moon is at 3 in the Morning; in the ſame page you ſay the Sun will be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſed the 16th of <hi>December,</hi> at our Midnight; and yet in <hi>Dec.</hi> you ſay it is at one in the Morning; what! is there the difference of an hour between the Full Moon and her Eclipſe, and between the New Moon, and the Sun's Eclipſe? for ſhame do not be guilty of theſe fulſome Contradictions; prithee forbear correcting others, till you mend your own Faults, and underſtand better, or elſe you and your Family muſt go to the Colledge in <hi>Moor-fields:</hi> With theſe fulſome Errors, remember you tell us in your lying <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemerides, That the Sun's Eclipſe in</hi> June <hi>will be almoſt total.</hi> And in your <hi>Popiſh Almanack</hi> for 1693. you ſay, <hi>it will be but half a Digit:</hi> What Stuff this is to come from <hi>John Gadbury? fie</hi> John <hi>fie,</hi> are not you aſham'd of this? I am ſure you may, only I think you are paſt ſhame.</p>
            <p>And for the Quotation <hi>Jack</hi> carps at, I do aſſure him he is mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken; and whoſoever will look into <hi>Ptolomy, Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Quadripar.</hi> they will find the ſame Words, only in another Language; but for that Book I am ſure, <hi>John</hi> underſtands it not, nor never will; and therefore <hi>Proclus</hi> and <hi>Ptolomy</hi> are indeed all one to him.</p>
            <p>And as to the Second Eclipſe I mentioned, I did not take it from the patch'd up 20 years <hi>Ephemeridies</hi> that he falſly calls his, but from <hi>Mezzavachis,</hi> who doth aſſure me it was almoſt 7 Digits and a half, and ſaid, <hi>almoſt three Parts of the Moon's Body would be dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned:</hi> Pray then where is the Error that this fooliſh Fellow makes a noiſe about? In the two other <hi>Eclipſes</hi> he ſhews his Malice and his Ignorance in carping at my Quotation of <hi>Junctine;</hi> for the Texts there alledged, he knows very well they are printed by <hi>Junctine</hi> in his <hi>Speculum;</hi> and if ſo, Where is the cauſe for this ſilly rattle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed Fellow's Noiſe and Clamour? I am afraid really the Fellow muſt to <hi>Bedlam,</hi> and his Family too, if the Mad-Moon doth not prove the more kind to him; and ſo I come to the <hi>NB.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 17. Here he wriggles about, and I cannot tell well what he would be at, but at laſt he quarrels with my falſe <hi>Grammar;</hi> pray ſee his Ability to correct me, in <hi>pag.</hi> 81 and 82. <hi>opus Reformat;</hi> but at laſt he concludes my meaſure of Time is mortal, becauſe I uſe the word Expire: Pray <hi>Jack</hi> tell me if your Meaſure of Time doth
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:94020:17"/>
not expire, how do you know when your Direction begins to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate? for according as I underſtand it, when the meaſure of an Ark of Direction is out, or the Years, Months, and Days, are expired, allowed by that Meaſure, then the Direction begins to ſhew its Effects; if ſo, I am right in the Word <hi>Expire;</hi> and again, if your Meaſure is as you ſay, Immortal, and hath no End, how is it a Meaſure? for Time it ſelf, that is to be meaſured, is not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, then how can your Meaſure be ſo? and every Meaſure is extremely leſs in length, than the thing meaſured; but this Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is one of the exquiſite Points of your Nonſence; and beſides, thou art one of the impudenteſt Fellows in nature; for I ſay, at the <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> of ☉ ♄, the ſame is on the Moon's radical place, ſhe at his Birth being near 6 degs. in ♌, and when the Sun came to ſix in ♌, he was applying to the Square of <hi>Saturn,</hi> within about five Degrees: What! doth ſuch ſilly Cavils as theſe become the Great man in <hi>Brick-court? Fie for ſhame, learn more wit, or elſe more modeſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pag. 18. I do confeſs the <hi>French</hi> King's <hi>Nativity</hi> is as certainly mine, as the <hi>Merlini Liberati Errata</hi> was <hi>Jack Gadbury</hi>'s; nor do I diſown any of it, tho I confeſs it was done by the approbation as well as the inſtigation of <hi>J. G.</hi> nor do I deny his <hi>Nativity</hi> to be a great one; but this doth not hinder him from being a <hi>Tyrant</hi> and an <hi>Oppr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſor,</hi> and I was deluded by <hi>Jack</hi> at that time, to print that <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant</hi>'s <hi>Nativity,</hi> and it was he that provided me a Book ſeller, with whom I ſuppoſe he agreed to bubble both the Printer and the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, for I never had a penny for my Copy, tho perhaps he had; <hi>Remember</hi> Stow's <hi>Chronicle,</hi> Jack.</p>
            <p>At the ſame time that he encouraged, and put me upon doing this thing, he then alſo gave me a Copy written by himſelf, called <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trum horum;</hi> Rome <hi>or</hi> Geneva, <hi>Never a Barrel better Herring;</hi> deſigned againſt all <hi>Religions,</hi> but moſt chiefly againſt the Reformed <hi>Protestant Profeſſion;</hi> this he bid me carry to one Mr <hi>Reynolds</hi> a <hi>Bookſeller</hi> (which I did) and deſire him to print it with my Name to it; but he refuſed to do it (asking me; <hi>If I knew what it was?</hi>) I told him, <hi>I knew nothing but the Title</hi> (believing my <hi>Friend J. G.</hi> would not have put an ill thing upon me); he ſaid, <hi>It was an ill thing, and against Religion, and therefore he would not print it;</hi> and the <hi>Copy</hi> I bel eve I have by me ſtill; and had this <hi>Villanous Book</hi> been alſo done in print, I doubt not but he would abuſe me for it, as well as he doth for the other; and to ſay the truth, it is his Doctrine and Method, but both falſe; yet it was my Labour and Pains taken in the compiling of it; all which I do at preſent diſown in this my Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:94020:17"/>
having a Method more agreeable to Nature, and the real Motion that we all contend for; and let this Fellow, if he can, ſhew what I have ſaid in any Predictions about him, that is oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to the very matter he relates. — But at the bottom of that page, he ſays, <hi>He owns it his duty to ſerve the King and Country in Purſe and Perſon, and this he reſolves to do cordially:</hi> You ſerve the King both with Purſe and Perſon! yes, ſo you did in 1690. with your <hi>Popiſh Declaration,</hi> and your <hi>Treaſonable Letter.</hi> You boaſt of your Loyalty! I ſuppoſe you mean to your <hi>Popiſh King:</hi> Do you think <hi>Non-reſiſtance</hi> is not a Duty now, as well as it was ſix or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Years ago? leave off your canting and your lying, and learn your Duty to God and our King, without <hi>Popiſh</hi> and <hi>Knaviſh Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 19. If there were nothing elſe to prove that <hi>Pamphlet</hi> writ by <hi>J. Gadbury,</hi> this Page of it ſelf is ſufficient; for I think no man but him hath a Face ſo qualified, to put ſuch a Falſhood upon the World, and to entertain his Reader with the relation of a Story, that gives the lie to his own knowledge, at the ſame moment; and therefore I do refer it to every, or any Reader for judgment, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided he hath not been of too many Religions. He chargeth me with ſaying, <hi>That I knew no ground of a difference in the Year</hi> 1690. and now in 1693. <hi>I pretend to find one:</hi> I ſtand amazed to think any man ſhould have ſuch a Stock of Impudence to tell ſuch a notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lie with ſo much Confidence, and therefore pray hear the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fairly. In the <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to my <hi>Almanack</hi> 1690. I have theſe Words, <hi>The Ground of our Difference I know not, and would deſire him to tell that; but when I was beyond Sea, and he thought he ſhould never ſee me more, he wrote a Book againſt me, called a</hi> Reply, <hi>ſo full of Malice, Ill Language, Lies, and malicious Expreſſions, almoſt impoſſible to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, or that a Villain ſhould be ſo ungenteel to a man in Tribulation, that never gave him the leaſt occaſion imaginable; if I did, let him ſpeak,</hi> &amp;c. Now it appears that he takes the firſt ſix or ſeven words of the <hi>Paragraph,</hi> and from thence ſays I tell the world, <hi>I know no cauſe of difference:</hi> 'Tis true, I ſay ſo ſtill, <hi>I know no cauſe he had to begin that Quarrel with me;</hi> and he knows he began, for he prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted firſt, and abuſed me baſely, and that was the Cauſe on my ſide; but the Cauſe on his, and the reaſon why he writ that villanous <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply</hi> in 1687. I know not, and therefore would deſire him to tell it, for it is not his Impudence, and <hi>Popiſh</hi> way of lying ſhall ſilence me, ſo long as I have Juſtice on my ſide: The firſt occaſion of our difference did indeed appear to me, in the end of <hi>September</hi> 1680.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:94020:18"/>
he and I then being in company, I called his <hi>Couſin Cellier</hi> (ſo he then own'd her) a hard Name, for which I thought he would have beaten me, but that I was not willing to it: There was alſo ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Reaſon about that time; for one day he told me in ſome An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, <hi>That I had ſpoil'd my Fortune by writing againſt Popery in my Prodromus,</hi> a little thing that was publiſhed about the time he was in <hi>Goal;</hi> theſe things might broil in his Stomach all this while, as indeed I know they did; and tho I have heard by others of his ſcurrilous Reflections on me, I always ſpoke of him with reſpect, and gave him a good Report; and however theſe might be the occaſion of difference on his ſide, I did not take notice of any thing t ll he printed in 1687. and that was the cauſe I contend with him; but what cauſe and reaſon he had to write that I know not, and deſire him to tell me; for the cauſe of that Book muſt be the cauſe of our difference.</p>
            <p>But at laſt he quarrels with <hi>Merlin</hi>'s <hi>Black-Thumb!</hi> Alas, poor <hi>John!</hi> ſet <hi>Merlin</hi>'s <hi>Black Thumb</hi> againſt <hi>Jack Thimble</hi>'s <hi>Black Life:</hi> What! meddle with my Trade, when you know what a Broad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide I have at you? indeed <hi>John</hi> I thought you had been better fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with Senſe, than I find you are; remember from whence you came, you are indeed hot and heavy, like a <hi>Taylor</hi>'s <hi>Gooſe;</hi> and therefore have at you in your own Way, and your old Trade.</p>
            <q>
               <l>'Tis a Champion great,</l>
               <l>My M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe doth relate</l>
               <l>With St. <hi>George</hi> and the reſt of the Fighters</l>
               <l>How with Finger in Neck</l>
               <l>He did boldly attack</l>
               <l>His Boſom Friends, and his Backbiters.</l>
               <l>Croſs-Legg'd on his Throne,</l>
               <l>He govern'd alone,</l>
               <l>Notwithſtanding his Hell was ſo near,</l>
               <l>He call'd for his <hi>Bodkin,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Thimble,</hi> that odd thing</l>
               <l>And obediently both did appear.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And becauſe he ſhall not think I am grown dull and barren in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagrams, I'll give him one in anſwer to his, tho not ſo Gallows high.</p>
            <p>John Gadbury
<q>
                  <l>Bury'd in a <hi>Hog.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As Hell of old did to the Swine retire,</l>
                  <l>So the <hi>old Sow</hi> did the <hi>young Boar</hi> inſpire</l>
                  <l>She got the Swine, Hell form'd this <hi>vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Bog,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And all her Pains was bury'd in a <hi>Hog.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 20. As to the Book he here rails at, and reviles, there are more A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>trological Truths in that contemptible Treatiſe, than e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he knew, or was able to inform the World of; and for his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it a railing beaſtly Treatiſe, I ſhall only ſay this, <hi>That I have a Naſty beaſt-like Fellow to deal with;</hi> and let him, if he thinks fit, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Aſtrologick part, and let that which he calls railing alone; and I do aſſure him, I ſhall kiſs his hand in Print again very ſpeedily.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:94020:18"/>At laſt he asketh me, if <hi>J.G.</hi> is ſo bad a man as I repreſent him to be, how doth he keeps clear of the Law, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Why <hi>John!</hi> were not you indicted by Mr. <hi>Godden</hi> for debauching his <hi>Wife?</hi> Were not you taken up in <hi>Charles</hi> the Second's Time, and kept in Priſon 8 or 10 Weeks? Were you not taken up in the <hi>Summer</hi> 1690. and in cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtody 8 or 9 Weeks, and both theſe for Crimes againſt the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and do you call this eſcaping the Law all this while? take your ſelf by the Memory again, and conſider. And whoſoever will but conſider the number of men deſtroyed in 1685. Blood being then ſpilt in Paſtime; and the Blood-hunting then, and in ſome Years before, he will ſoon be able to tell whether they were Bloody Reigns or not?</p>
            <p>I find in the Concluſion that Mr. <hi>J. G.</hi> is going to publiſh a <hi>Book</hi> called the <hi>Ungrateful Daemon diſpoſſeſs'd,</hi> I believe it will be a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ingenious thing, becauſe it is founded upon <hi>Conjuring;</hi> for who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever goeth to diſpoſſeſs a <hi>Daemon,</hi> in <hi>Engliſh</hi> a <hi>Devil,</hi> muſt do it by <hi>Prayers,</hi> or by <hi>Conjuring;</hi> by <hi>Prayer</hi> he cannot, his Life and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation is too wicked to effect ſuch a thing; but by <hi>Conjuring</hi> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell what to ſay to it, becauſe it is a new Trade he hath taken up, and that he learn'd it of his <hi>Prieſts,</hi> with their <hi>Hoc eſt Corpus:</hi> But methinks if he could do it by <hi>Conjuring,</hi> he might have caſt the <hi>Devil</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut of his <hi>Wife</hi> by this time, ſhe being mad, and he having had her about ſix years, long enough to have done that, which to this day he hath not done; I am afraid he is a meer <hi>Juggler,</hi> and cannot conjure: However I will at the End of my Book, give him a <hi>Copy</hi> of <hi>Verſes</hi> to put at the beginning of his; And they are as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth:</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>In Commendation of <hi>J. Gad.</hi> and his New Conjuring Book.</head>
            <l>CALL good Aſſiſtance in, the Men of Note,</l>
            <l>Go fetch the <hi>Tapers, Rod</hi> and <hi>Conjuring-Coat:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Now draw a Circle, draw it plain and fair,</l>
            <l>And in the middle place our <hi>Conjurer;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Make all the horrid Signs and Characters,</l>
            <l>To raiſe in the Spectators dreadful Fears;</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:94020:19"/>Write all the Thundring Frightful Names thereo n,</l>
            <l>Of <hi>Anael, Raphael, Zadkiel, Metroton,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Pauiel, Caſſiel, Tetragrammaton:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>With <hi>Rod</hi> and <hi>Book</hi> in hand, let him appear,</l>
            <l>Arm'd with the <hi>Croſs,</hi> that makes his Devils fear:</l>
            <l>Now is he ſafe, now let the Work begin,</l>
            <l>Now let him call his <hi>Captain Devil in,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>With all his <hi>Rake-hell Tribe,</hi> Old <hi>Satan</hi> by,</l>
            <l>And bring with them <hi>Hell</hi>'s <hi>Grand Artillery.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>His <hi>Joyful Fiends</hi> thus met, with fury hurl'd,</l>
            <l>We'll leave them now to <hi>diſpoſſeſs</hi> the World;</l>
            <l>Go call <hi>Queen Mab,</hi> and Great <hi>King Oberon,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And ask them what the Devil they have done?</l>
            <l>To ſend a Fool, a Fool that prides himſelf,</l>
            <l>Of being Chief, nay, the Chief <hi>Sovereign Elf;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Satan</hi>'s Succeſſive Heir, the <hi>Errant Fairie,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>That pinch'd by Night the Thighs of <hi>Joan</hi> and <hi>Mary;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>This Prince of <hi>Daemons,</hi> that commands each <hi>Elf,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>What! caſt them out of others, not thy ſelf?</l>
            <l>The Reaſon's plain, he to himſelf is civil,</l>
            <l>He is a Compound, and the moſt part <hi>Devil:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Then who can think the <hi>Elf</hi> from's ſelf will run,</l>
            <l>That <hi>Satan</hi> e're will diſpoſſeſs his own.</l>
            <l>What! caſt out <hi>Daemons</hi> now, is Trade grown ſlack,</l>
            <l>True <hi>Juggler</hi> ſtill, here's honeſt <hi>Conjuring Jack.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Your Wife</hi> is mad, pray let your Skill appear,</l>
            <l>Begin at home, caſt out the <hi>Devil</hi> there.</l>
            <l>But hold, to give Advice in that I'm loth,</l>
            <l>You <hi>Two</hi> being one, one <hi>Devil</hi> ſerves you both:</l>
            <l>Nay, 'tis a frugal way, can you agree,</l>
            <l>One <hi>Single Devil</hi> ſerves a whole <hi>Family.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>But what's one <hi>Devil</hi> to the mighty Hoſt,</l>
            <l>When <hi>Jack</hi> himſelf can of his <hi>Legions</hi> boaſt.</l>
            <l>Well, by theſe Titles now may'ſt thou prefer,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Thy Prince</hi>'s Slave, and Hell-born <hi>Conjurer.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Go <hi>Curſe</hi> and <hi>Conjure</hi> with your <hi>Popiſh Crew,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Your <hi>Croſs,</hi> your <hi>Dagon-Deity</hi> and You.</l>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
